<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The necessitie of righteousnes. Or A profitable and fruitfull sermon vpon the fift chapter of the Gospell of S. Mathew. vers. 20. Preached and penned by that famous, learned, iudicious, orthodoxall, holy, wise, and skilfull preacher and servant of God, now deceased, and with his God triumphing in Heaven, Iohn Randall, Batchelour of Divinitie, pastour of St Andrewes Hubbart in little East-cheape London, sometimes fellow of Lincolne Colledge in Oxford. And now published, to the glory of God, the edification of his Church, and the honourable memoriall of the author, by William Holbrooke, preacher of the Word of God in the church aforesaid</title>
            <author>Randall, John, 1570-1622.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 48 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10393</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20675</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115634</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850852</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850852</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16084</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10393)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16084)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1078:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The necessitie of righteousnes. Or A profitable and fruitfull sermon vpon the fift chapter of the Gospell of S. Mathew. vers. 20. Preached and penned by that famous, learned, iudicious, orthodoxall, holy, wise, and skilfull preacher and servant of God, now deceased, and with his God triumphing in Heaven, Iohn Randall, Batchelour of Divinitie, pastour of St Andrewes Hubbart in little East-cheape London, sometimes fellow of Lincolne Colledge in Oxford. And now published, to the glory of God, the edification of his Church, and the honourable memoriall of the author, by William Holbrooke, preacher of the Word of God in the church aforesaid</title>
                  <author>Randall, John, 1570-1622.</author>
                  <author>Holbrooke, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I[ohn] D[awson] for Nathaniel Newbery and William Sheffard, and are to be sold at their shops in Popes-head Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1622.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The necessitie of righteousnesse.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16084:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16084:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE NECESSITIE OF RIGHTEOVSNES.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>OR</hi> A PROFITABLE AND FRVITFVLL SERMON Vpon the fift Chapter of the Goſpell of S. <hi>Mathew.</hi> verſ. 20. Preached and Penned by <hi>that famous, learned, iudicious, Orthodoxall, holy, wiſe,</hi> and skilfull Preacher and ſervant of God, now deceaſed, and with his God triumphing <hi>in Heaven,</hi> IOHN RANDALL, <hi>Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>elour of Divinitie, Paſtour of</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Andrewes Hubbart</hi> in little <hi>Eaſt-cheape</hi> LONDON, Sometimes Fellow of <hi>Lincolne</hi> Colledge in OXFORD.</p>
            <p>And now publiſhed, to the glory of God, <hi>the edification of his Church, and the honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Memoriall of the Author, by</hi> WILLIAM HOLBROOKE, Preacher of the Word of God in <hi>the Church aforeſaid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>I. D.</hi> for <hi>Nathaniel Newbery</hi> and <hi>William Sheffard,</hi> and are to be ſold at their Shops in <hi>Popes</hi>-head Alley. 1622.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:16084:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16084:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RELIGIOVSLY AFFECTED LADY THE LADY BENNET, Wife to Sir <hi>Iohn Bennet,</hi> all hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe here, and hereafter <hi>bee multiplied.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S you were a great loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer by the death of that ſervant of God, maſter <hi>Randall,</hi> who was to you (whilſt he lived) a faithful and able coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeller, both ſpiritually and bodily, and from whom you received great ſatisfaction, direction, and comfort
<pb facs="tcp:16084:3"/> in all diſtreſſes, whenſoever you reſorted to him, as you haue oft confeſſed, to the glory of God. And as your loue was great to him, manifeſted many wayes, whilſt he liued, and in his ſickneſſe, and ſince his death, by your much lamenting, and weeping for the death of him, that a man may ſay of you, and your loue to this man departed, as the <hi>Iewes</hi> did of our Saviour, concerning his loue to <hi>Lazarus,</hi> when he wept over him, <hi>Behold, how he loued him,</hi> Ioh. 11.36. So I know your <hi>Ladiſhip</hi> will be readie to receiue, and yeeld your beſt countenance to whatſoever was his; wherevpon I haue made bolde, in teſtimony of my thankfulneſſe to your <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſhip,</hi> for your readineſſe (lately) to doe me good, here to Dedicate vnto you a Sermon of his, Preached and penned by his owne hand, as it commeth to your view: I need not perſwade your <hi>Ladiſhip</hi> to accept it, I know the child ſhall be welcome, both for it owne and Fathers ſake, eſpecially, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering, that it will (in ſome ſort) ſupply, the loſſe and abſence of a profitable and deare friend, whom though you cannot heare, nor ſee any more ſpeaking vnto you, and
<pb facs="tcp:16084:3"/> counſelling <hi>viva voce,</hi> yet you may heare and ſee counſelling you by this and other of his writings; for friends abſent, whether liuing or dead, ſpeake by writing, when they cannot be perſonally preſent, and <hi>viva voce</hi> ſpeake. Conſider then (good <hi>Madam</hi>) when you reade this, and other of this mans writings, you heare him ſpeaking vnto you, and counſelling you, and this will be motiue enough, to perſwade your <hi>Ladiſhip</hi> to entertayne what is here preſented vnto you. The Lord Ieſus, that Counſeller of his Church and People, by his Spirit counſell, direct, and comfort you, and ſo ſupply the lacke of this, and other friends: he being in ſtead of all; To him I doe and will commend your <hi>Ladiſhip</hi> for euery good bleſſing by Prayer:</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>And in Him I reſt, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge my ſelfe, your</hi> La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſhips <hi>much bounden friend,</hi> WILLIAM HOLBROOKE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:16084:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16084:4"/>
            <head>TO THE RELIGIOVS GENTLEVVOMAN, M<hi rend="sup">ris</hi> THOMASIN OVVEFIELD, All happineſſe in this life, <hi>and that which is to come be multiplied.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Ood M<hi rend="sup">ris</hi> Owefield;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Conſidering your caſe to be the ſame with the Lady <hi>Bennets</hi> aforeſaid, both in reſpect of your loſſe in <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Randall,</hi> who was, as to her, ſo to you, a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Counſeller every way, as you haue often confeſſed, and alſo in reſpect of your loue to him, both in life, ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, death, and ſince, onely the odds is on your ſide, in that you haue not onely in your owne particular, ſuſtey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned a loſſe, but your Family alſo, by the death of that worthy ſervant of God, who oft inſtructed them in the way of the Lord: conſidering, I ſay, your caſe to be like vnto the foreſaid Ladies, in the foreſaid reſpects, I haue made bolde, as a teſtimony of my thankefulnes, for your loue divers times ſhewed vnto me, to Dedicate this
<pb facs="tcp:16084:5"/> Worke alſo to you, that your loſſe may (in ſome ſort) be ſupplyed, by ſeeing and hearing him ſpeaking to, and counſelling you, in <hi>Print,</hi> whom you ſo reioyced to ſee and heare ſpeake, when he was living by word of mouth, I make no queſtion of your acceptance of what was his, as this was both penned and Preached by him, as here it commeth to your View: My deſire ſhall be to God for you, to bleſſe this and all the labours of his, which you haue inioyed, any way, to the furthering, edifying, and confirming of you and yours vnmoueably in your preſent faith, which God grant for his Chriſts ſake, in whom I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>And reſt your much bounden Friend WILLIAM HOLBROOKE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:16084:5"/>
            <head>THE NECESSITIE OF RIGHTEOVSNES.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>MATHEVV 5.20.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>For I ſay vnto you, Except your righteouſneſſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed the righteouſneſſe of the Scribes and Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, you ſhall not enter into the Kingdome of Heaven.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S ſoone as our SAVIOVR had wonne certaine Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples and followers to himſelfe, ſome, by his Word and expreſſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, as <hi>Peter, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew, Iames,</hi> and <hi>Iohn,</hi> whom he called from their Nettes to follow him, that he might make them fiſhers of men, as it is in the fourth Chapter of this Goſpell, verſe 22. and ſome, by his Doctrine, teaching in their Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues, and Preaching the Goſpell of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, verſe 23. and other ſome, by his Miracles, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb facs="tcp:16084:6"/> the Lunaticke, curing the Palſie, diſpoſſeſſing the Devils, and helping every ſickneſſe, and every diſeaſe among the people, as it is verſ. 24. ſo that there followed him great multitudes out of <hi>Galilee,</hi> and <hi>Decapolis,</hi> and <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and <hi>Iudea,</hi> and from beyond <hi>Iordan,</hi> as it is in the 25. verſe of that Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: As ſoone (I ſay) as he had ſo done, he went vp into a Mountaine; and his Diſciples thither re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorting to him, he opened his mouth, and made a Sermon to them, as it is in the beginning of this Chapter.</p>
            <p>In which his Sermon, having firſt propoſed vnto them whole troupes and multitudes of bleſſings, and withall, ſhewed them how to attaine thereunto, he giues them certaine neceſſary inſtructions for their vocation, and that eſpecially they ſhould be carefull in doing good workes: that, whereas they were the Salt of the earth, they muſt not be vnſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voury, but by their good example ſeaſon the hearts of the people; and whereas they were the light of the world, they ſhould ſo ſhine before men, that they ſeeing their good workes, might glorifie their Father which is in heaven, as it is verſ. 16. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Law and the Prophets of God, are the onely rule of good workes, therefore verſ. 17. hee puts them in mind of them both, ſhewing, that he is not come to deſtroy them, but to fulfill them; and therefore howſoever he preaches faith, and the free remiſſion of ſins, and the glad tydings of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, yet he is ſo farre from abrogating the Law, from diſanulling good workes, that contrariwiſe, the chiefe end of his comming was to eſtabliſh
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:16084:6"/> good workes, and to fulfill the Law. For as a Pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that hath firſt caſt his ground, of white or black, or any ſuch colour, when afterward he ſtaines it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine in ſundry places with ſundry other colours, to faſhion his worke, cannot be ſayd to deſtroy or quite deface his ground, but rather to garniſh it, and fill it vp, and make it perfect: even ſo our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, comming to teach vs the right ſenſe and vſe, and end of the Law, cannot be ſayd to deſtroy the Law, but rather garniſhes, as it were, the ground of the Law with his true Interpretations, and right v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, ſupplying all the imperfections thereof, and fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling it vp in every poynt, ſo that, as it is in the 18. verſe, not one iot or title thereof ſhould eſcape vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulfilled. And whereas the Law was, before, depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and ſo the people ſeduced and deluded by the Scribes and Phariſees, therefore in this his Sermon he examines their falſe gloſſes from point to point, and reformes all their depravation of the Law, lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this Verſe, which I haue read vnto you, as the ground of that which followeth: wherein he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwades, and brings his Diſciples out of conceit with their former Teachers; he ſeekes to purge them of the old leaven of the Phariſees, and would not haue them retaine the leaſt ſmatch or reliſh thereof; the very righteouſneſſe of the Scribes and Phariſees muſt become odious to Chriſts Diſciples;<note place="margin">Text.</note> 
               <hi>Your righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe,</hi> ſayth he, <hi>muſt exceed the righteouſneſſe of the Scribes and Phariſees.</hi> Neither was this onely a counſell or exhortation, as though it onely were a thing meete and convenient for his Diſciples to be better then the Phariſees, and he would faine haue
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:16084:7"/> them ſo to be; but this is an abſolute Precept, of great waight and importance, it is as much as their ſoules are worth;<note place="margin">Text.</note> for, except this be ſo, <hi>they ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver enter into the Kingdome of heaven.</hi> And that they might conſider the better of it, and beleeue it more certainely, he tells them, that this Doctrine is not from earth but from heaven, it comes not from man but from God,<note place="margin">Text.</note> 
               <hi>I ſay vnto you,</hi> ſayth our Saviour, that it is ſo indeed. <hi>For I ſay vnto you, except your righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, &amp;c.</hi> So then this Scripture is a kind of Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination or Threatning, which our Saviour makes to his Diſciples. Wherein we may obſerue; Firſt, the Aſſeverant manner of ſpeech here vſed; Chriſt ſayth, <hi>I ſay vnto you.</hi> Why, all this Chapter is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by Chriſt, for it is a Sermon that he Preached to his Diſciples; but he would haue this Doctrine ſticke more cloſely to their hearts, and throughly conſidered aboue all other poynts, therefore he layes it before them, nay, he faſtens it vpon them with ſpeciall termes of Aſſeveration, <hi>I ſay vnto you.</hi> Secondly, the Dutie which here is required of them and in them of vs, <hi>their righteouſneſſe muſt exceed the righteouſneſſe of the Scribes and Phariſees.</hi> Thirdly, the Penaltie here threatned them vpon default of the performance of that Dutie, even the loſſe of Heaven it ſelfe, <hi>you ſhall not enter into the Kingdome of Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, of the Aſſeveration. <hi>I ſay vnto you.</hi> As if our Saviour ſhould thus haue ſpoken to his Diſciples;<note place="margin">1. <hi>I.</hi>
               </note> The Scribes and Phariſees haue ſeduced you, and taught you all this while erronious Doctrine; they were blind Leaders of the blind, but <hi>I</hi> that am the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:16084:7"/> light of the World, <hi>I</hi> teach you better Doctrine; <hi>I</hi> ſay vnto you otherwiſe then they did. The Scribes and Phariſees taught you, that externall and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward righteouſneſſe was ſufficient to ſalvation; they are lyers: but <hi>I</hi> that am the Truth, <hi>I</hi> ſay vnto you otherwiſe. The Scribes and Phariſees taught you, that the Law goeth no farther then to the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man, it ſpeakes nothing to the inward moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and affections of the heart; they are deſtroyers and corrupters of the Law: but <hi>I</hi> that came not to deſtroy the Law, but to fulfill it, <hi>I</hi> that was preſent at the making of the Law, <hi>I</hi> that was an agent in the publiſhing of the Law, <hi>I</hi> that came out of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome of my Father, to teach the right ſenſe, and the true vſe of the Law, <hi>I</hi> ſay vnto you otherwiſe, that except your righteouſneſſe exceed, &amp;c. Or, as if our Saviour ſhould thus haue ſpoken to his Diſciples: See that you make no doubt of the truth of this Doctrine, for it is <hi>I</hi> that ſpeake it, therefore beleeue it certainely; <hi>I ſay.</hi> You need not ſuſpect any dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in it, for it is <hi>I</hi> that ſpeake it, therefore receiue it ioyfully; <hi>I ſay.</hi> Let it not ſlip you without due meditation, for it is <hi>I</hi> that ſpeake it, therefore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member it carefully; <hi>I ſay.</hi> See that you faile not to yeeld preſent obedience to this Doctrine, for it is <hi>I</hi> that ſpeake it, therefore practiſe it dutifully, <hi>I ſay</hi> vnto you.</p>
            <p>I <hi>ſay.</hi> Very fitly doth this word, <hi>Say,</hi> agree with <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> the perſon of him that ſpeaks it. He ſayth here <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Say.</note> I <hi>ſay,</hi> who is indeed properly <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>verbum,</hi> the Subſtantiall Word himſelfe. This is peculiar to Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, the Sonne of God, the ſecond perſon in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:16084:8"/> the ever-bleſſed Trinitie, to reveale vnto vs the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crecies of God, and by the words of his mouth, to teach vs the way of our ſalvation. At ſundry times and in divers manners, ſaith the Apoſtle, God ſpake in old time to our Fathers by the Prophets, but in theſe dayes he hath ſpoken vnto vs by his owne Sonne, <hi>Heb. cap.</hi> I. <hi>ver.</hi> 1, 2. He hath <hi>ſpoken,</hi> ſayth the Text, not onely by his Meſſengers, but even mouth to mouth, and face to face, as we ſee in this place, I <hi>ſay</hi> vnto you.</p>
            <p>Many things our Saviour knew within himſelfe, which were not meete to be imparted to his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples; but this was a matter that concerned them very neere, and therefore he telles them of it, I <hi>ſay</hi> vnto you. Many things our Saviour was to tell his Diſciples, but they muſt firſt be growne to ſome better perfection, according to that, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 16.12. I haue many things to ſay vnto you, but you cannot beare them as yet: but this was a principall ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worke of that holy Religion which he was after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to build vp in his Diſciples hearts, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is one of the firſt leſſons he teaches them, one of the firſt things that he ſayth vnto them. Many things our Saviour would haue his Diſciples acquainted withall, even whileſt they were novices in the Faith, whereof he giues them but onely as it were an inkling, to whet on their witts by ſome Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rables and darke ſpeeches, leaving it to be found out by their owne induſtrie: but this was a mayne poynt of their ſalvation, and therefore without any Parable, without any circumlocution, without any trope or figure at all, he telles them of it openly
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:16084:8"/> and plainely, in very expreſſe termes, I <hi>ſay vnto you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vnto you.</hi> I ſpeake not to the Scribes and Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> they are ignorant,<note place="margin">You.</note> and let them be ignorant ſtill; but it is <hi>you</hi> that I deſire to inſtruct, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſay vnto <hi>you. You,</hi> that looke for a portion in my Kingdome, this is a leſſon for <hi>you. You,</hi> that I haue made ſpeciall choiſe of to preach my Goſpell, this is a leſſon for <hi>you.</hi> I ſay it to <hi>you,</hi> firſt, that <hi>you</hi> might learne it and practiſe it your ſelues; and I ſay it to <hi>you,</hi> that afterwards, <hi>you</hi> may teach it to others. For as it was in that miraculous banket, when fiue thouſand people were fedde with fiue Barly loaues and two fiſhes, our Saviour tooke the victuals, and gaue firſt to his Diſciples, and the Diſciples gaue to them that were ſet downe, as it is <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6.11. even ſo in this ſpirituall banquet of feeding ſoules, our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour firſt giues this heavenly food to his Diſciples, I ſay vnto <hi>you,</hi> ſayth he, that his Diſciples might af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward deliver and impart the ſame vnto others, Briefly vnderſtand him thus; I ſay vnto <hi>you;</hi> as if he ſhould familiarly conferre with them on this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; I am your Maſter, and <hi>you</hi> are my Diſciples, and I would faine haue <hi>you</hi> to be ſaved, howſoever all the world ſpeedes beſides, therefore I ſay vnto <hi>you;</hi> young beginners and petie Schollers are taught by thoſe that are of a higher fourme, and of longer ſtanding then themſelues are, but the greateſt and beſt Schollers are taught by the Maſter himſelfe: and therefore, howſoever your predeceſſours being but (as it were) young Schollers, haue beene taught by <hi>Moſes</hi> or <hi>Elias,</hi> or ſome one of the Prophets and
<pb facs="tcp:16084:9"/> Prieſts, yet <hi>you,</hi> as being the higheſt Schollers in the Schoole of my Goſpell, <hi>you</hi> I teach in my owne per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, I ſay vnto <hi>you,</hi> that <hi>except your righteouſneſſe, &amp;c.</hi> And ſo much for the opening of the true meaning of the Aſleveration. Now let vs ſee what profitable Obſervations may hence be gathered for our In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> And firſt, concerning the Author and Teacher of this Doctrine, which is Ieſus Chriſt himſelfe, who here ſayth, <hi>I ſay.</hi> Behold here, Beloved, the wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full loue of God towards mankinde: He had vſed the Miniſtery of the Patriarkes to inſtruct their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies; but that did not ſatisfie him. He had vſed the Miniſtery of <hi>Moſes</hi> in the Law, to inſtruct his people; but that did not ſatisfie him. He had vſed the Miniſtery of the Prophets to inſtruct them; but that did not ſatisfie him. He had vſed the Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Prieſts and Levites to inſtruct them, but that did not ſatisfie him: yea, he had vſed the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of <hi>Iohn Baptiſt,</hi> one that was greater then a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, and yet that did not ſatisfie him. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore after all thoſe, he ſent downe his owne Sonne into the world, to ſpeake vnto men, face to face, and to inſtruct them in the matters of their ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And this his loue will appeare yet to be the greater, if we conſider the deſperate eſtate which the world in thoſe times was come vnto; all the foundations of the earth being out of courſe,<note place="margin">Pſal. 82.5.</note> as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſpeakes,<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 5.9.</note> and the whole world then, lying downe in wickedneſſe, as the Apoſtle ſpeakes: and there is as much here inſinuated by our Saviour, when he withdrawes his Diſciples from the Scribes
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:16084:9"/> and Phariſees, as being corrupted themſelues and corrupting others. They ſate in the chaire of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> and from their mouthes the people were to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire the Law, and the whole ſubſtance of ſalvation both for life and doctrine: they were the very light and the eye of the body, of the Church that then was. Now the eye being wicked, and the light being darkned, oh, how great was the darkeneſſe of the whole body? In the middeſt of this darkeneſſe came the true light of the world, to cleare the Law, to cleare the Doctrine of ſalvation, to looſe the workes of the Devill, as himſelfe ſpeakes;<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 3.8.</note> that whereas the Scribes and Phariſees, Sathans inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, had taught the people hypocriſie, he might convert them from being hypocrites, and teach them true righteouſneſſe; and whereas they had ſeduced the world into the pathes of deſtruction, he might rectifie their courſe, and ſhew and lead them the ready way to everlaſting life.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>1</label> Here then we learne, with what reverence to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace, and in what price to eſteeme the Goſpell, Chriſt himſelfe being both the Author, and the Meſſenger thereof. If there were no further reaſon, but onely becauſe it is the wholeſome Doctrine of our owne ſalvation, we were to eſteeme of it very highly: but now that we ſee it comes from heaven, that Chriſt himſelfe is both the Author and Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger of it, oh, how deare and precious ought it to be vnto vs? This is the Vſe which the Apoſtle makes of it, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> the three firſt verſes, where he compares the Goſpell with the word of Angels, that is, with the Law, which was given by the hands
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:16084:10"/> of Angels: If it were ſuch great danger to neglect the word whereof the Angels were the Meſſengers, how ſhall we eſcape if we neglect the great ſalvation, even the Goſpell wherof Chriſt himſelfe was a Meſſenger, who is much more excellent then all the Angels are, as he had ſhewed in the 4. ver. of the former chapter? So, likewiſe he compares it in the ſame terms of am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plification with the word of <hi>Moſes, Heb.</hi> 10.28.29. He that deſpiſeth the law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> he dieth without mercy; of how much ſorer puniſhment ſhall he be worthy, which treadeth vnder foot the Son of God, and the Goſpell whereof he is a Meſſenger? For as he had ſhewed before, <hi>cap.</hi> 3. <hi>ver.</hi> 3. Chriſt was far greater then <hi>Moſes.</hi> Were this imprinted throughly in our hearts, as it ought to be, that it is the word of Chriſt, we would be more eager and deſirous of it then now a dayes we are. Conſider, who is the Author of it, and what great danger there is in refuſing and neglecting it. We ſhould flock to Chriſt, as to our prey, if we were true Eagles, and reſort to him in great abundance; as we reade in the Goſpell, that the people ſtill preaſed vpon him, and ran after him, &amp; thronged him, for the earneſt deſire they had to heare him: but now, if <hi>Chriſt</hi> come to vs, ſo it is, but we will ſcarce ſo much as ſtep out of our doores to heare him; or if we doe, it is but ſcatteringly, and ſparingly, as if a man ſhould gather Grapes after the Vintage. Is this the fruit of ſo many happy yeares of the preaching of the <hi>Goſpel</hi> amongſt vs? And as this warnes vs to thirſt after the <hi>word</hi> more earneſtly, ſo alſo to embrace it more reverently; as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not the word of any mortall man, but (as it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed) the word of the true &amp; ever-living <hi>God.</hi> Thinke
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:16084:10"/> not, when you heare the <hi>word</hi> Preached, that it is the Miniſter only which ſpeaks it; for it is the Lord that ſpeakes it; and it is he that fayth as here to his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, <hi>I ſay vnto you.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>2</label> Againe, here we ſee, when we are in any error, whither we muſt goe to be reformed; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe, by whom the Diſciples are here reclaimed; for he is our only ſhepherd, that muſt bring vs home againe, when wee like loſt ſheepe are gone aſtray. He is our only Maſter, as he is called <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.8. who muſt correct all our errors. And whenſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver we feele any ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce or blindnes to poſſeſſe our hearts,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> he alone it is to whom we muſt pray with <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid, O Lord, open thou mine eyes, that I may ſee the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drous things of thy Law.</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, concerning his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livery of this Doctrine. He <hi>ſaith</hi> it. Wherein he giues vnto all the Miniſters of God, a notable patterne of that duty which is laid vpon them; they muſt not be tongue-tied, nor dumbe, but they muſt Preach &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver the Lords Meſſage vnto his people.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 9.16.</note> A neceſſitie is laid vpon vs, and woe vnto vs if we doe not Preach the Goſpell. It is the liuely voice of the Miniſter w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> God hath ordained as an effectuall inſtrument, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to faſten his word vpon the hearts of thoſe that ſhall be ſaved;<note place="margin">Iſaiah 42.1.</note> and therefore for <hi>Sions</hi> ſake wee muſt not hold our peace, nor be either afraid, or vnreadie to ſpeake. Our Saviour here by his example in ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to his Diſciples, doth ſhew vs our dutie, that we ought to Preach, and withall, that he cannot away with a dumbe Miniſtery. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, &amp; laſtly, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning his auditors; <hi>you,</hi> that is, his diſciples. Wherein we are to obſerue; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> firſt, that our Saviour had a very eſpeciall care over his <hi>diſciples,</hi> that wheras they were ſeparated
<pb facs="tcp:16084:11"/> to ſuch an excellent office, as to Preach the Goſpell; and retayning to ſuch an excellent Maſter as he was; therefore he would haue them to be more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently inſtructed, both for life and doctrine, then others were. He had placed them in the world, as a Cittie vpon the top of an hill; they were in open view, and every mans eye would be faſtened vpon them; and if any groſſe imperfection could be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpied in them, it would be a ſcandall to the Word, a reproch to their Maſter, a diſcredite to their cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and their evill example would ſpread it ſelfe like a running ſore to the infection of many others; and therfore he would haue them to be better then ordinary, their righteouſneſſe to exceed the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of the Scribes and Phariſees. Now as our Saviour ſaid, <hi>Mark.</hi> 13.37. Thoſe things that I ſay vnto you, I ſay vnto all men: ſo, the ſame which is here ſpoken to his Diſciples, he ſaith it alſo vnto you, beloved Brethren, and to as many of vs as ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede them in the worke of the Miniſtery. Let vs carry a watchfull eye over all our wayes, that we a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all others may be good examples. And as the Lord exhorts his people, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4.15. Though <hi>Iſrael</hi> play the Harlot, yet let not <hi>Iudah;</hi> ſo, let vs beware that (howſoever the Scribes &amp; Phariſees doe walke amiſſe, howſoever the common people be negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent in their wayes) yet we that are of the Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry be carefull to liue without giuing any iuſt oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of reproofe. We are, or ſhould be, the lights of the world; let not our miſdemeanour blemiſh that light of God that is within vs. We are, or ſhould be, the Salt of the earth; let vs not be vnſauoury,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:16084:11"/> leaſt we be caſt out vpon the dung-hill, among the filth and traſh of the world; let vs duely conſider, that the Lords owne credite doth in ſome ſort reſt vpon our ſhoulders; and that many other mens ſoules doe hang vpon our neckes; and that the Lord having giuen more vnto vs then vnto others, will require much more of vs then of others; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, for the good example of others; or, if that doe not moue vs, yet for the ſaving of our owne ſoules; or, if we regard not that, yet at the leaſt for the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifying of Gods moſt bleſſed name, in whoſe ſtead we are, I beſeech you, let vs euery one looke vnto our ſelues, as the Apoſtle counſels vs, and ſtriue to a greater meaſure of righteouſneſſe then ordinary, as our Saviour here willeth his Diſciples to doe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, we may here obſerue the wiſedome of our Saviour, in making ſpeciall choiſe of tractable and towardly minds, to whom he doth deliver this Doctrine. If he had vttered it to the Scribes and Phariſees, he had but ſtriven againſt the ſtreame: they would haue beene ſo farre from beleeving it, that contrariwiſe, they would haue withſtood it with all their power, and defied the Teacher, and beene more incenſed againſt him, as afterward they were in the like caſe. If he had Preached it to the common people, they would haue murmured a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, as being a new Doctrine, quite contrary to the wiſedome of their forefathers. If he had ſpoken it to the high Prieſts and Elders, they would haue accuſed him, ſpit on him, condemned him, cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied him, as afterward they did. Therfore he makes choiſe of better ſpirits then thoſe were; even ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:16084:12"/> as he knew, would be fitter to receiue, readier to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, and forwarder to practiſe his wholeſome In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions; he ſpeakes it to his Diſciples. Neither is our Saviour vnlike himſelfe in this courſe, for it was the ordinary tenour of his proceedings; he was alwayes very wiſe and wary in diſpoſing of the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of God. We reade of the high Prieſt, <hi>Mar.</hi> 14. 60. that he queſtioned with our Saviour about the deſtroying of the Temple, and building it againe in three dayes: but our Saviour would anſwere him nothing: he knew that the high Prieſt was not a fit man to heare of ſuch a matter. Likewiſe, of <hi>Herod Luk.</hi> 23.9. that he queſtioned with our Saviour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout many things, but our Saviour anſwered him nothing: he knew that <hi>Herod</hi> was not a fit Auditor for ſuch matters. Likewiſe of <hi>Pilate,</hi> Ioh. 8.38. that he asked our Saviour, what was Truth? But our Saviour, though he never was wont to ſmoother or ſuppreſſe the truth, giues him no anſwere: he knew that <hi>Pilate</hi> was not a fit Scholler to learne the truth. But aboue all other, he makes himſelfe moſt nice to the woman of <hi>Canaan,</hi> Mar. 15.26. Where he giues the reaſon of that action, and of all other of the ſame kind, <hi>becauſe it was not meet to take the childrens bread and to giue it vnto dogges.</hi> In the fourth of <hi>Luke,</hi> ver. 23. there we may ſee, that our Saviour had done many things in <hi>Capernaum</hi> of his owne accord, which he refuſed to doe in his owne Countrey, though they requeſted him earneſtly. What was the reaſon hereof? <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> telles you; it was <hi>incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulitas populi ſui,</hi> the vnbeliefe of the people. Nay, Chriſt himſelfe telles you, verſ. 24. that it was the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:16084:12"/> way wardneſſe and perverſeneſſe of his owne Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, who would not accept of a Prophet in his owne Country. You ſee therefore that our Saviour in great wiſedome doth here ſeparate and take his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples apart from the multitude into a mountaine, as it is in the firſt verſe of this Chapter, and there by themſelues alone, doth communicate theſe hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly myſteries vnto them, as being fitteſt for each other; they fitteſt for thoſe myſteries, and thoſe myſteries fitteſt for them.</p>
            <p>This Doctrine doth affoord vs a twofold Vſe. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>1</label> Firſt, here is matter of Imitation for vs that are of the Miniſtery, teaching vs, after the example of our Saviour, not to impart the myſteries of ſalvation to all men indifferently, but rather in wiſedome to make choiſe of our Auditors, as neere as wee can, to whom wee deliver them. A practiſe which our Saviour doth not onely countenance, by his exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, in the execution of his owne office, but he giues the ſame alſo in charge, by way of precept vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Diſciples in their Commiſſion. For ſo wee reade <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.11. <hi>Into whatſoeuer Cittie or Towne you enter, enquire who is worthy in it:</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, As many as you find to be vnworthy, and vnfit to heare your words, haue no dealing with ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, but depart from them, and ſhake off the very duſt of your feete, for a witneſſe againſt them. For as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> when they were amongſt the <hi>Babylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians,</hi> did hang vp their Harpes vpon the Willow trees, and would not ſing the ſongs of <hi>Sion</hi> in a ſtrange land, as it is, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 137.2, 3. Even ſo, the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of God are very ſparingly to be handled in
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:16084:13"/> the preſence of thoſe that are prophane and wilfull, who will be ready to ſcoffe at ſuch holy things, and to open their blaſphemous mouthes againſt them. And as <hi>Ezechias</hi> ſhould not haue ſhewed the King of <hi>Babylon</hi> his golden Veſtments;<note place="margin">Iſaiah 39.2.3.</note> So, neither ought the precious myſteries of God to be committed to wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vnbeleevers. I ſeeke not hereby to enforce an abſolute neceſſitie of this practiſe, as to be alwayes obſerved, as though every one of vs ſhould be bound to make ſpeciall choiſe of our Auditors for every thing we ſpeake, for this is a thing impoſſible; and, if it could be alwayes performed, yet there is no abſolute neceſſitie in it: for, <hi>Moſes</hi> muſt ſpeake to <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> though he know before hand, and be certified from the Lords owne mouth,<note place="margin">Exod. 3.19. Exod. 7.2.3.4.</note> that <hi>Pharaohs</hi> heart is hardened, and he will not heare him: And <hi>Ezechiel</hi> muſt ſpeake the words of the Lord vnto the <hi>Iewes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezech. 2.4.5.7.</note> though the Lord haue certainly forewarned him, that they are a ſtiff-necked, and rebellious peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and ſuch as will not heare him. But this is that which I would ſhew you, what an excellent and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary a thing diſcretion is in the Miniſters of God, and how chary we ought to be in delivering the myſteries of God, that we doe not giue ſuch holy things vnto dogs, nor caſt his precious pearles be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſwine. And ſeeing it is not in our power, ſtill to make choiſe of ſuch Auditors as ſhall be fit for our inſtructions, therefore wee muſt be wiſe in making choiſe of ſuch inſtructions as ſhall be fit for our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors. If thou doeſt light vpon thoſe that are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane and wilfull, to them, if thou ſpeakeſt any thing, thou muſt ſpeake of the judgements of God;
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:16084:13"/> but when thou meeteſt with more towardly &amp; trac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſpirits, ſuch as theſe Diſciples were, theſe thou muſt entertaine with ſuch a kindly leſſon, as this is which our Saviour here vſeth to his Diſciples.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>2</label> The ſecond Vſe of this Doctrine is for the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, for ſeeing our Saviour doth here make ſpeciall choiſe of thoſe to whom he doth reveale theſe my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, here is an <hi>Item</hi> for the people, that if they do not feele the meſſage of ſalvation in themſelues, nor their hearts inwardly admoniſhed in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to true obedience, they are to take a ſtrong pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudice againſt themſelues, that ſurely the Lord doth as yet eſteeme them to be vtterly vnworthy and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit for all goodneſſe, that (like dogs and ſwine) they are not admitted to ſuch holy Pearles. If the Goſpell be hid, ſayth the Apoſtle, it is hid to them that are loſt, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.3. And they whom the Lord hath not made acquainted with the matters of their owne ſalvation, they are as yet in a very hard and damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble eſtate. It is a fearefull thing to be debarred of the meanes of our ſalvation, as theſe Scribes and Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees in ſome ſort were debarred; in that the Lord doth not vtter the courſe of ſalvation within their hearing. On the other ſide, it is a very ioyfull and comfortable bleſſing, that the Lord ſhould teach vs how we may be ſaved, as here he teacheth his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, acquainting them in private, and very famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arly with the ready way to the kingdome of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. Let therefore every man throughly ſift and examine himſelfe, whether, by all the hearing that ever he hath had benefit of, he findes this fruit within himſelfe, that he is inwardly admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, and inclined in his owne ſoule, to leaue the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:16084:14"/> common and ordinary way of the world, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take himſelfe to a more ſtrict and ſevere courſe of life, ſuch as is peculiar but to few, and yet to all Gods children. For this indeed is the very preſent caſe of theſe Diſciples; whom our Saviour would weane from the ordinary courſe of the Scribes and Phariſees, and adviſe them a Peculiar courſe of his owne direction. And when thou haſt thus examined thy ſelfe, if thou doeſt find any ſuch effect within thy ſoule, then thou muſt record and magnifie the infinite mercies of Almightie God, to thy owne endleſſe comfort: but if thou doe not feele this fruit within thy ſelfe, then muſt thou know that as yet thou art in the feareful eſtate of condemnation, and that God hath left thee to take the ordinary courſes that the world is wont to take, that ſo thou maiſt be condemned togither with the world. And this conſideration will make thee, if thou haſt any ſpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kles of grace in thee at all, to rowſe vp thy ſelfe, and continually to ſtriue with Almightie God in hearty Prayer, that for his owne glory ſake, he will vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe at the length to reveale and open vnto thee the myſtery of thy ſalvation, and withall, to open thy heart, that thou maieſt vnderſtand the ſame, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue it, and yeeld ready obedience thereunto. And thus much concerning the firſt principall point that I propounded to your godly conſideration, out of this Scripture, namely, the manner of his ſpeech, or the termes of Aſſeveration, whereby our Saviour would faſten this leſſon vpon his Diſciples. I haue ſtood vpon it the longer, becauſe (as you ſee) it hath miniſtred vnto me good ſtore of ſuch matter as is fit and very pertinent to this preſent Aſſembly.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:16084:14"/> Now proceed we to that which followes, ſo farre forth as the time ſhall permit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Except your righteouſneſſe, &amp;c.</hi>] <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall poynt which hence I obſerved, was, the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie which is here required of them, and in them of vs;<note place="margin">Text.</note> 
               <hi>their righteouſneſſe muſt exceed the righteouſneſſe of the Scribes and Phariſees.</hi> Wherein we are to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue, firſt, the matter of that Dutie, it is <hi>righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe:</hi> ſecondly, the qualitie of that <hi>righteouſneſſe,</hi> which is here expreſſed, partly, by way of Negati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, not <hi>ſuch a righteouſneſſe as is that of the Scribes and Phariſees;</hi> and partly, by way of Affirmation,<note place="margin">Text.</note> but ſuch as beſeemes the Diſciples of Chriſt, the true Children of God, <hi>your righteouſneſſe;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Text.</note> and third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the meaſure of that righteouſneſſe ſo qualified, it muſt not be ſcant, but abound, and exceede, your righteouſneſſe muſt <hi>exceede.</hi> Or els,<note place="margin">Text.</note> that we may draw it into a narrower Diviſion; The thing requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, is <hi>righteouſneſſe;</hi> which our Saviour deſcribes by way of compariſon, with the righteouſneſſe of the Scribes and Phariſees: In whoſe righteouſneſſe he ſeemes to taxe a double defect, and requires in the righteouſneſſe of his Diſciples, the ſupplying of both thoſe defects. Firſt, their righteouſneſſe, it was but counterfeit, it was not good enough, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the righteouſneſſe of Chriſts Diſciples muſt be a better righteouſneſſe: and ſecondly, their righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe was very ſcarſe and ſparing, and therefore the righteouſneſſe of Chriſts Diſciples muſt be more; there muſt be greater ſtore of righteouſneſſe in them then was in the Scribes and Phariſees, ſo that it muſt exceed, both in goodnes &amp; in greatnes.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, of the matter of this Dutie, which is <hi>righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe:</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:16084:15"/> whereby we are to vnderſtand the whole o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience which a man doth owe vnto God, both in reſpect of his faith, and in reſpect of his life, both for doctrine, and alſo for manners. For indeed, ſo much is enforced exactly by the Antitheſis, or Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition here ſpecified, whereas exception is made both againſt the Scribes, and the Phariſees too. For, as it ſhall afterwards (God willing) more plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appeare, the Scribes, they were skilfull in the knowledge of the Law; and the Phariſees, they were preciſe and formall in the practiſe of the Law: the Scribes were the men of greateſt learning; and the Phariſees, the men of exacteſt living, that theſe times did affoord. Therefore exception being taken againſt them both, it is very plaine that our Saviour would haue his Diſciples, both to know the Law better then the Scribes, and to practiſe the Law bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then the Phariſees; <hi>Your righteouſneſſe,</hi> ſayth he, muſt exceed the righteouſneſſe of the Scribes and Phariſees both. God, as he hath appointed and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared a Kingdome in heaven, ſo, becauſe that is the holy of holies, there is no way for any prophane or vncleane thing to enter into it: and therefore the Lord requires that every one that would enter ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, ſhould be righteous and holy; according to that <hi>Pſal.</hi> 118.20. This is the gate of the Lord, the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous ſhall enter into it. It is the wedding garment which every one of vs muſt be covered withall, if we would be fit ghoſts for that wedding feaſt which the Lord hath prepared in Heaven. The Scripture makes mention of a twofold righteouſneſſe, Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe inherent, and righteouſneſſe imputed. Firſt, there is a righteouſneſſe that is within vs, our
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:16084:15"/> obedience to the will of God; or, at leaſt, our ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to performe it as neere as we can: and ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, there is a righteouſnes that is without vs, which being inherent in Chriſt, is apprehended of vs by a true and a liuely faith, and ſo is imputed vnto vs, &amp; accounted ours, as really, as if it were within vs. For true righteouſneſſe is nothing els but the fulfilling of the Law; as contrariwiſe, Sinne is nothing els but the tranſgreſſion of the Law; and if we do performe the Law of God our ſelues, here is inherent righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, here is our ſanctitie and holineſſe of life. Nay, if we do not performe it to the full (for this ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver any mortall man could reach vnto, but the Son of God alone) yet if we endevour and ſtriue to it the beſt we can, God, that accepts of the will as of the deed, as the Apoſtle ſpeakes, doth in great mercie e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme it for righteouſneſſe. But becauſe this our righteouſnes is defectiue, &amp; too light to be waighed in the ballance of Gods juſtice, therefore wee muſt goe out of our ſelues to ſeeke for a better righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, ſuch as may ſtand before God without control<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and be admitted without any exception; and this is to be found in Chriſt alone, who onely hath fulfilled the Law in every point: which if we faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully lay hold vpon, perſwading our ſelues aſſured<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that whatſoever Chriſt hath done, he hath done it for vs, then we make it become our righteouſneſſe. The inherent righteouſnes is the matter of our ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification, &amp; the imputed righteouſnes is the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of our iuſtification. Now our Saviour requires here of his Diſciples, that they ſhould be furniſhed with both theſe ſorts of righteouſnes. Howbeit, he aymeth principally at our inherent righteouſneſſe,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:16084:16"/> that is, our holineſſe of life, wherein we muſt exceed the Scribes and Phariſees. So then you ſee, that this is an exhortatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to good works. For howſoever our Saviour came downe from Heaven to Preach the Goſpell, and the free remiſſion of our ſins through faith in his bloud, yet he would not haue men to think, that faith were enough to ſaue them without good workes, but as many as looke to be partakers of his merites, they muſt be careful to avoid ſin, and zealous of good works, and with all their power en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devour themſelues to fulfill the Law of God. It is a controverſie betwixt vs &amp; the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the neceſſitie of good workes; they charge vs, that we teach the doctrine of faith alone, &amp; tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple the doctrine of good workes vnder our feet, and that we proclaime a Goſpel of liberty and ſecurity. But this is a manifeſt ſlander againſt vs; for we doe teach the doctrine of good workes, and exhort men to be careful in ſeeking to pleaſe God by holines of life, as earneſtly as they doe. True indeed, that wee deny good workes to be neceſſary in the worke of our juſtification; for it is faith alone that doth iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie vs in the ſight of God: but wee hold them to be abſolutely neceſſary to our ſalvation: ſo that our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries doe very deceitfully change the ſtate of the queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that is betwixt vs, bearing the world in hand that we deny all good works, therby to diſcredit &amp; reproch our religion. No beloved we for our parts doe very conſtantly hold againſt all the Libertines in the world, that there never was any man, nor ever can any man ordinarily be ſaued without good works. We do indeed magnifie the doctrine of faith; but doe we thereby diſanull the doctrine of good
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:16084:16"/> workes? God forbid, ſaith the <hi>Apoſtle:</hi> Nay, rather we eſtabliſh the law of workes, by eſtabliſhing the law of faith. For when we preach vnto men the ſingular loue of Ieſus Chriſt, wherewith he hath loued them, even aboue his owne life, &amp; his own precious bloud, which is the matter of our faith: preſently we make vſe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, as being a very forcible motiue to perſwade men, that they ſhould endevour themſelues by all meanes poſſible to requite this loue of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> with loving him againe, which is the matter of our good works. But to leaue our adverſaries, and to come to the preſent mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it ſelfe, which we haue in hand. Our Saviour here exhorting his Diſciples to righteouſneſſe, ſhewes vs plainely, what an odious thing it is in his ſight, for a man to be a profeſſed Chriſtian, and Scholler of his, when he hath no care to glorifie the name of God, &amp; to grace his owne profeſſion, by liuing righteouſly in this preſent world: nay, he ſhews further, that all that ever he hath done for vs, he hath done it to this end, that we might ſtill be converſant in the exerciſes of righteouſneſſe. A thing which the Apoſtle hath ſet downe in more plaine and expreſſe termes, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.11. where he ſaith, <hi>the grace of God which bringeth ſaluation to all men, hath appeared;</hi> &amp; to what end? that we ſhould liue in ſecurity, that we ſhould turne it in wantonnes? No; but to this end, that <hi>we ſhould deny all vngodlines, and worldly luſts;</hi> and <hi>that we ſhould liue ſoberly, &amp; righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly, and godly in this preſent world.</hi> And as this duty is laid vpon all thoſe that profeſſe the name of Ieſus Chriſt, ſo it concernes vs of the Miniſtery more then any other; let vs not content our ſelues with a vaine ſhaddow of Faith, and let not vs thinke, that it is our knowledge that can ſaue vs; for vnleſſe we haue righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes,
<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
